A Guide to the Arlington Hall, Collected Materials, 1929-1993
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Arlington Hall, Collected Materials, 1929-1993
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
RG 3
10 boxes.
Arlington Hall Station (Va.)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Arlington Hall Alumnae Association and the Commander, Intelligence and Security Command.
Historical Information
Arlington Hall was an operating junior college and high school from 1927 to 1942. It suffered financial problems in the 1930s, and finally became a non profit institution in 1940. In 1942 the facility faced condemnation and was taken over by the Secretary of War under the Second War Powers Act. Deemed essential for the war effort, the school became the headquarters of the Army Signal Corps, later the Intelligence and Security Command; at this time it became known as Arlington Hall Station. Important work in cryptography, including the breaking of enemy codes, was done there during World War II. Following the creation of the Defense Intelligence Agency in 1961, a major center of that agency was housed there.
In 1986, the Department of State began a study of Arlington Hall as a site for their Foreign Service training. The National Guard Bureau also assessed the site for a center in 1988. These projects have been realized. Today both the National Foreign Affairs Training Center and the Army National Guard Readiness Center operate out of Arlington Hall. Other items in the collection show the significant interest in the Arlington Hall property by the surrounding community, including a campaign to limit government expansion on the site, and return the property to Arlington.
Scope and Content
The Arlington Hall Record Group covers the history of the Arlington Hall Junior College, with materials published between 1928 and 1993. Most of the materials came from alumnae and are in the form of yearbooks, newsletters, college catalogs, scrapbooks, photographs, and assorted ephemera, reflecting the use of Arlington Hall as a college. The rest of the material has been gathered from various sources over time, and reflects later uses of the property. The collection currently measures about 12 linear feet.
This collection is active. We will continue to add material about the college obtained through the Alumnae Association or other sources, and will also include information on current and future use of the property.
Arrangement
Record Group 3 is arranged in seven subgroups. The first three of these contain materials from the original college, including yearbooks, school publications and a student scrapbook. Programs and copies of "The Yarn" from 1938 and 1939 were found in a donated 1939 yearbook. Subgroup 4 holds alumnae materials gathered over the years, some arranged in notebooks, and alumnae bulletins which contain information on reunions. Subgroup 5 addresses the broad coverage of special events from 1927 to the present, including the War Department's takeover of the facility. This group also houses some more recent land use reports.
Subgroup 6 contains photographs in three series. The first covers college life. The second shows various military scenes and activities at Arlington Hall Station. The third includes alumnae activities such as reunions and other ceremonial occasions. Subgroup 7 houses two videotape productions. The first is a history of Arlington Hall produced by the Army, and the second covers the opening of the State Department's Foreign Affairs Training Center.
There is a large group of photographs in the alumnae scrapbook in Subgroup 4. While many of these reflect the history of the school, several document the history of various alumnae families. Subgroup 6 includes pictures of school activities and of the buildings and grounds. There are also pictures from the Signal Corps era, scenes of building construction and military activities. Alumnae history in later years is also represented in photos of reunions and other programs involving the new Army and State Department facilities on the property. Almost all the images are black and white. There are no negatives. All the photos fall under Center for Local History photo policies and procedures. The staff can provide details.
Contents List
- Arlington Hall (Junior College) Yearbooks
  - 1928-1942 (Bound volumes in boxes, many duplicates) 1928-1942 (Box 1-5)
- Arlington Hall (Junior College) Other Publications
  - Catalogs
    - 1929-1930 (Box 6)
    - 1935-1936, 1936-1937 (Box 6)
    - 1937-1938, 1938-1939 (Box 6)
    - 1939-1940 (Box 6)
    - 1940-1941 (Box 6)
    - 1941-1942 (Box 6)
  - Publicity brochures (4) 1930-1939 (Box 6)
  - Magazine, "Arlington Yarn" 1931-1932, 1938, 1939, 1942 (Box 6)
    1938, 1939, and 1942 issues are OVERSIZE.
  - Newspapers (scattered, OVERSIZE) 1933-1942 (Box 6)
  - Address books 1935-1936, 1954 (Box 6)
- Arlington Hall (Junior College) Ephemera
  - Scrapbook, student 1941-1942 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous; forms, logo, letterhead, envelopes, school song, 2 poems 1927-1942 (Box 6)
  - Programs, 1939 (Box 6)
- Arlington Hall (Junior College) Alumnae
  - Scrapbooks 1927-1942 (Box 6)
    Scrapbook cover housed separately, OVERSIZE.
  - Alumnae lists, geographical
    - 1927-1941 (in notebook format) (Box 6)
    - 1975 and 1993 (Box 6)
  - Alumnae bulletins, notices, correspondence (scattered) 1939-1994
    - 1939-1994 (Box 7)
- Arlington Hall Background
  - Histories
    - Introductory History of VENONA and Guide to the Translations, National Security Agency, n.d. (Box 8)
    - VENONA Historical Monograph #2: The 1942-1943 New York-Moscow KGB Messages, National Security Agency, n.d. (Box 8)
    - VENONA Historical Monograph #3: The 1944-1945 New York-Moscow KGB Messages, National Security Agency, n.d. (Box 8)
    - VENONA Historical Monograph #4: The KGB in San Francisco and Mexico, the GRU in New York and Washington, National Security Agency, n.d. (Box 8)
    - School and military station: articles, monographs (scattered dates, some undated) (Box 8)
    - Army Historical Survey: questionnaires, correspondence 1977-1978 (Box 8)
    - Army historical videotape production: correspondence 1984 (Box 8)
    - General Correspondence 1942-1990 (scattered) (Box 8)
  - Newsclippings
    - School and military station 1933-1991 (scattered) (Box 8)
    - Further development of property 1982-1990 (scattered) (Box 8)
  - Reports and notes
    - Use of property, various authors (most undated) (Box 8)
    - Location of Defense Intelligence Agency building at Arlington Hall, Congressional Hearing 1964 (Box 8)
    - Preservation of Arlington Hall, Arlington Historical Society Newsletters 1982, 1987 (Box 8)
    - Arlington Hall and Future Site of Foreign Service Institute, Technical Report 1986 (Box 8)
    - National Foreign Affairs Training Center, Master Plan Report (in Virginia Room files) 1988 (Box 8)
    - National Foreign Affairs Training Center, Environmental Assessment (in Virginia Room files) 1988 (Box 8)
    - Arlington Hall Station, Historic Resources Assessment (in Virginia Room files) 1988 (Box 8)
    - National Guard Bureau Consolidation to Arlington Hall, Environmental Assessment 1988 (Box 8)
    - Farewell to Arlington Hall and INSCOM Day: program, invitation, list of alumnae attendees, correspondence 1988 (Box 8)
    - National Foreign Affairs Training Center: planning, public hearing, Congressman Frank Wolf notes, correspondence 1985-1989 (Box 8)
    - Historic American Buildings Survey, Arlington Hall Station, correspondence 1990 (Box 8)
    - National Capital Planning Commission agendas with correspondence (re: Arlington Hall Station) 1989-1990 (Box 8)
    - National Foreign Affairs Training Center Inauguration: program, invitation, correspondence 1993-1994 (Box 8)
- Arlington Hall Photographs
  - Junior College
    - Activities (27 prints) (Box 9)
      - Archer from brochure
      - Art class
      - Biology class, students at microscopes
      - Cooking class
      - Costume party
      - Dance party
      - Golf game
      - Garden party
      - Harpist from brochure
      - Horse jumping (two sizes, one in OVERSIZE box)
      - Lacrosse game
      - Mimeograph operators
      - Pageant, outdoor, audience seated in foreground
      - Parade, equestrian formation
      - Physical education class
      - Rifle team
      - Riders, champion horse
      - Sewing class
      - Student, escort in garden
      - Students boarding buses
      - Students canoeing
      - Students, dormitory room
      - Swim team (names on back of print)
      - Tea party
      - Tennis foursome
      - Typing class
      - Queen and throne (OVERSIZE)
    - Groups (15 prints) (Box 9)
      - Archery team, exterior
      - Teachers: Carrie Sutherland and Frances Jennings, exterior
      - Students and fireplace
      - Formal gowns, bouguets, exterior
      - Formal gowns, interior stairway
      - Figures, seated, front steps
      - Riders, Equestrian trophies
      - Figures, main entrance, grouped between columns
      - Queen, court at outdoor pageant
      - Student, unidentified portrait found in Spinning Wheel, Volume 4 (Brooks Studio) 1931
      - Student group seated around garden fountain
      - Tennis group
      - Students, Tidal Basin, cherry blossom time
      - Student, unidentified found in 1940 Spinning Wheel belonging to Bliss Brown
      - Riders, horses in front drive, two cars in background (OVERSIZE)
    - Interiors (4 prints) (Box 9)
      - Coat of arms, school 1927
      - Entrance foyer
      - Parlor
      - Sitting Room
    - Exteriors (14 prints) (Box 9)
      - Campus, rear view, from yearbook
      - Catterbox Tea House (color)
      - Foot bridge in woods
      - Garden arbor
      - Garden fountain
      - Garden walk, flagstone
      - GArden walk, flower-lined, stone bench
      - Garden walk looking tward entrance door and standing figures
      - Main building and lily pond
      - Main building end, foreground shrubs blooming
      - Main entrance, from yearbook
      - Pathway, woods
      - Roadway, campus
      - Main building, entrance drive, pond (panorama) (OVERSIZE)
  - Military Station
    - Military Construction (10 prints) (Box 9)
      - Bulldozer, construction in background
      - Excavation, foundations and frames, new buildings
      - Excavation, power shovel and dump truck
      - Excavation, power shovel
      - Field kitchen for workers
      - Foundation, new construction
      - Framing installation, dump truck left center
      - Roofing new building, construction braces
      - Buildings, temporary work
      - Warehouses, open fronts
    - Activities (16 prints) (Box 9)
      - Print shop, casting type, metal ingots and waste in background
      - Chow line
      - Laboratory, photographic (?), light box in table
      - Office, card files and maps in the rear, in foreground a typewriter and woman with letter file
      - Office, large room, workers at tables, card files right center, three women front row
      - Office, military personnel mostly, sign in rear: "Stop. Don't go until 4:30"
      - Office, personnel at desks, war bond poster, map of Japan on wall
      - Office, workers, posters: War Bonds, Armed Forces Radio Service
      - Firehouse crowd at outdoor function
      - Paper shear, operator
      - Print shop, press, operators
      - Print shop, collators, staplers, operators
      - Training class, maps on easel and wall
      - VIP arrival (unidentified)
      - Warehouse, workers with mail bags (?)
      - Work area with printers, fan-fold paper
    - Interiors (3 prints) (Box 9)
      - Barracks, potbellied stoves
      - Post exchange, toiletries with artificial flowers
      - Soda fountain and short order counter, juke box
    - Exteriors (13 prints) (Box 9)
      - Building, unidentified, row of pine trees center
      - Building, unidentified, "screen porch" right center
      - Building, unidentified, window boxes
      - Bus stop, sign: 15th and K Street Line
      - Commander's house, front view
      - Commander's house, rear three-quarter view
      - Firehouse, 2 fire trucks out front
      - Operations Building A, completed 1942
      - Operations Building B, completed 1943
      - School building, Arlington Hall, rear corner (?)
      - School building, Arlington Hall, front with flag and statue of soldier (color)
      - Warehouse, truck and loading platform
      - School building, Arlington Hall, main entrance with cannon (OVERSIZE)
  - Alumnae Activities
    - Reunions, activities with Army and State Department (Box 9)
      - Award ceremony and picnic, INSCOM, alumnae group (10 people) (U.S. Army photo by SP4 Schroder) 1988
      - Award ceremony and picnic, INSCOM, alumnae, family members, woman in wheel chair (U.S. Army photo by T. Gardner, Sr.) 1988
      - Award ceremony and picnic, INSCOM, Major General Soyster and alumnae, snap shooter at right (U.S. Army photo by SSG Bills)
      - Award ceremony and picnic, INSCOM, 7 alumnae and 2 Army people (U.S. Army photo by T. Gardner, Sr.) 1988
      - Award cemermony and picnic, INSCOM, MG Soyster and alumnae group with family members (U.S. Army photo by SP4 Schroder) 1988
      - Reunion, alumnae, Mayflower Hotel 1954
      - Reunion, alumnae, with Lawrence Taylor, Director, Foreign Affairs Training Center 1994
      - Army Farewell to Arlington Hall, time capsule, MG Soyster and alumnae 1988
      - Army Farewell to Arlington Hall, time capsule, MG Soyster and alumnae viewing certificate 1988
- Videotape Productions
  - History of Arlington Hall 1986 (Box 10)
  - National Foreign Affairs Training Center Inauguration 1993 (Box 10)